901 N. Monroe St.
Arlington, Va., 22201
703-599-3188
matt@optimizewebsolutions.com

# Matt Birch Professional Resume

### **Experience Summary**

Specialize in content creation for a digital audience to be distributed across multiple tractional channels (social media posts, blogs, newsletters, press releases, etc.).

16 years of experience producing blog posts, social media copy and news articles. Also engage and interact with audience (crowdsourcing).

12 years of experience creating multimedia content (short-form videos, GIFs, podcasts, etc.).

8 years of experience building websites (portfolio, publishing platforms, brochure, Ecommerce, etc.).

Possess strong copy editing skills and proficient in AP Style.

## **Employment History**

Self

Feb. 2022 to Present

#### **Content Writer**

Produces content for brands and businesses as a ghostwriter.

Specialize in social media posts, blog articles and email newsletter copy.

Utilizes SEO copywriting skills to hit KPIs (Key Performance Indicators). Boosts clients' conversion rate, generates awareness and/or drives revenue.

**Optimize Web Solutions** 

Oct. 2021 to Present

## **Web Developer**

Builds custom websites for small and medium businesses (SMBs) using HTML5, CSS and JavaScript. Focus on user experience, leveraging responsive web design principles.

Writes content for brands as a ghostwriter: Social media posts, blogs and email newsletter copy.

Utilizes SEO copywriting skills to hit KPIs. Boost clients' conversion rate, generate awareness and/or drive revenue.

Conducts website audits to optimize site performance.

The Sports Daily

Dec. 2013 to Oct. 2021

#### **Editor-in-chief**

Managed all daily operations for The Sports Daily—a network of 100+ sports blogs that produces content primarily covering the "big four" U.S. professional sports leagues.

Implemented SEO (Search Engine Optimization) SOPs for all blogs to increase organic website traffic.

Built WordPress websites for blogs both in and outside the TSD network.

Forged strategic partnerships with both content and advertising partners.

Leveraged social media to engage readers, share content and react to live events in real-time.

Collaborated with brands for content marketing, link building and more.

OBXtek Inc.

Sept. 2012 to May 2016

#### **Staff Accountant**

Uploaded semi-monthly timecards from payroll system to Deltek accounting software.

Set up new contracts and task orders.

Reconciled subsidiary ledgers to general ledger balances.

Recorded deposits from bank account to cash receipts ledger.

#### **Associate Editor**

Worked cooperatively with B/R's editorial team to curate fresh, compelling and relevant content for the fifth-most-visited sports media website.

Planned and executed NFL coverage strategy while meeting weekly content budget requirements.

Managed a large team of content producers that specialized in producing indepth NFL content packages.

Generated compelling, SEO-friendly headlines which appealed to a broad audience.

Live-blogged NFL games to provide analysis, commentary and scoring updates in real-time while interacting with B/R's audience.

Evaluated aspiring columnists who wished to join the B/R NFL team as content producers.

Promoted content via B/R's Twitter account.

Richmond Times-Dispatch

Sept. 2010 to Dec. 2010

# **Junior Reporter**

Wrote articles centered around the fan experience at high school football games to complement RTD's match reports.

Sat on RTD's news desk to monitor breaking news.

# Education

# Virginia Commonwealth University

Obtained Bachelor of Science (B.S.) degree, Mass Communications (print journalism), in May 2011.